# Catherine Kimani

Nairobi, Kenya +254720356644 <u>katewkimani@outlook.com</u> https://ke.linkedin.com/in/katekimani

Excellence driven engineer whose passion is applying software technology to solve business needs. Experienced in translating users' needs for software capabilities into requirements, designing software systems, testing software systems for functional and user experience quality standards, and managing software development teams.

### Skills

- Hiring and team management
- Web application development (Python, Ruby, PostgreSQL, MySQL)
- Systems design
- Data engineering
- Software quality assurance

# **Experience**

2018 - 2020

### Senior Software Engineer / Andela, Nairobi

Andela invests in Africa's most talented software engineers to help companies solve the technical talent shortage and build high performing distributed engineering teams.

#### Role and Achievement:

Participate in leadership activities to provide mentorship and interview potential engineers. Perform tech lead roles on partner engagements to manage communication with partner team, have 1:1 checkins with the team and ensure sprint tasks are well defined.

o Serving as a tech lead for an Austin based startup, where we integrate 3rd party vendors onto the freight platform. Tech stack: Python/Django, Python/FastAPI, PostgreSQL, AWS, Mongo

2016 - 2018

### Engineering Manager / Lendable, Nairobi

A New York based fintech startup that helps SMEs in Africa access affordable receivables financing from investors in the US and Europe.

### Role and Achievement:

Handled the day to day management of the Nairobi engineering team including onboarding, 1:1 checkins and performance reviews. Wrote code to maintain and extend the in-house deal platform. Tech stack: Python/Flask, PostgreSQL, AWS

 Successfully advocated for a fair and transparent compensation structure and this led to the company overhauling the entire compensation policy to have members in different locations compensated within market benchmarks. 2015 - 2016

### Entrepreneur in Training / MEST, Accra

A 12-month entrepreneurship training program for African youth funded by the Meltwater foundation.

#### Role and Achievement:

Studied business skills to build a successful startup and applied the training on the concept of an online marketplace for African fashion designers to sell to global consumers.

 Built an e-commerce platform MVP and carried out direct sales to designers with 4 successful signings.

2014 - 2015

## Business Analyst / M-KOPA Solar, Nairobi

The leading 'pay-as-you-go' energy company lighting up over 400,000 homes in rural areas that are off the grid by selling them home solar kits on credit which is repayable in instalments over 365 days using mobile money.

#### Role and Achievement:

Engaged with the customer care team to create requirements that were useful in supporting their processes. Translated these requirements into features, wireframes and business process models. Engaged with the development team to prioritize the features and plan the delivery on the sprints. Tested the developed systems to verify that the requirements were met and trained the customer care team on the new system changes.

• From a user base of 100, the ticket system was in use in 4 countries and had an average of 1000 tickets logged and tracked daily.

2010 - 2014

# Senior Quality Assurance Engineer / Cellulant, Nairobi

A mobile payments company which connects banks, merchants and MNOs to enable them provide services to their customers via mobile channels in the form of mobile banking services, merchant payments and mobile apps.

Joined as a junior developer, progressed to a business intelligence analyst and later became a quality analyst.

#### Role and Achievement:

Responsible for creating a test plans and driving the test automation effort for the company's software. Participated in peer reviews and team training to ensure skills transfer. Assisted in resource planning for projects and ensuring progress is communicated in a timely manner especially for challenges faced.

 From a full manual tests process, implemented automation for the main system which covered 80% of the web application and helped reduce the regression testing time to an average of 10 hours from 200 hours previously.

### **Education**

2010

### BSc. Software Engineering / Kenyatta University, Nairobi

Second Upper Class (2:1)

# **Interests & Volunteer Experience**

### PyConKE Conference 2017 - Present

I volunteer in the organizing committee for the PyCon conference in Nairobi. I am responsible for communication, registration of the attendees and online marketing. The conferences have been successes and help many students get involved in the Python community.

### M-KOPA Solar Lewa Marathon Team Training 2015

I volunteered to be part of the training organizers for the company team in the 2015 Lewa Marathon. We made the training routes and handled the communication to the team on participation and qualifications and had a great turn out for the charity event with minimal fuss.

#### Cellulant Staff Welfare Committee 2012-2014

I was a member charged with secretarial roles for the pioneer Cellulant Welfare committee for two years. I ensured the social welfare obligations were met by ensuring funds were released on time to affected employees and events.

#### Automation of the Business Intelligence Process Jan-June 2011

There was a gap for the business whereby the data used in reports was inaccessible and inconsistent. I implemented an automated framework which runs statistics automatically at midnight and makes them readily available for use, removing the delay and guesswork from the process.

#### **Test Automation**

I championed the transition from manual to automated tests at Cellulant by personally learning and pushing for the adoption of Test Driven Development processes and Continuous Integration within the team. During the tenure, all projects written encompassed the use of Unit tests and this led to increased traceability and transparency in the testing process.

#### Interests

- o I organize the monthly meetups for Python Nairobi.
- o I take online courses on Coursera and to date I have received several statements of completion.